本劇改編自聖經  將始終盡力保持《聖經》真諦
某些場景含暴力鏡頭  請觀眾自行斟酌
《聖經》前情提要
Previously on The Bible.
起初
In the beginning,
上帝創造天地
God created heaven and earth.
然而人罪惡令他失望
Then human failings led him to destroy his creation.
錯誤的選擇,錯誤的決定
Wrong choices, wrong decisions.
從諾亞後，開始了一個新時代...
After Noah, a new beginning...
和一個亞伯拉罕的承諾
and a promise for Abraham.
上帝同我說話了
God has spoken to me.
他將指引我們去新的家園
He will lead us to a new home.
他保證我的後裔會多如繁星
He has promised descendants as numerous as the stars.
但由埃及奴役，亞伯拉罕的後裔遭受了痛苦
But enslaved by Egypt, Abraham's descendants suffered...
直到一個新的領袖出現
Until a new leader emerged...
誰會成為以色列最偉大的英雄
who would become Israel's greatest hero.
你是誰
Who are you?
我是摩西
My name is Moses.
上帝派我回來  給你們自由
God has sent me... to set you free.
自由  他們能自由選擇成為奴隸還是死人
Freedom? They're free to choose...
被奴役或是死亡
slavery or death!
我這一生都被法老奴役
All my life, I have been Pharaoh 's.
我再也不會是個奴隸了
I will never be a slave again.
約書亞  上帝與我們同在
Joshua, God is with us.
賴德
Ride!
耶和華
Lord!
跟我走
Follow me!
上帝讓我們擺脫了奴役
God has delivered us from slavery.
去應許之地繁衍生息
We're going to live in the promised land.
亞伯拉罕的夢想  我們的未來
Abraham's dream is our future.
你是我們人民的未來  約書亞
You are our future now, Joshua.
你必須延續上帝與亞伯拉罕子孫的夢想
You must take the land promised to Abraham.
摩西帶領以色列人
Moses has led the Israelites...
到應許之地的邊垂
to the edge of the promised land.
在約書亞帶領下,他們要征服它
Under Joshua, they must conquer it.
《聖經》
第03集-家園
耶和華   摩西傳下這十誡時
Lord, I was with Moses...
我和他在一起
when he handed down these commandments.
我見證了這份聖約
I was witness to the covenant,
見證了賜予我們聖潔國度的承諾
the promise of a holy nation.
助我建立這個國度
Help me to forge that nation,
領導你的子民繼承他們的土地
to lead your people to inherit their land.
約書亞
Joshua!
主帶我們離開了埃及
- The Lord brought us out from Egypt. - Right!
他承諾將賜予我們這片土地
He promised us this land.
很快
And soon,
就會是我們的了
it will be ours.
過來
Come.
你們準備好了嗎  -我們會搜查整個城市
- Are you ready? - We'll search the whole city.
找一條能讓我進去的路
Just find me a way in.
我們必須攻下耶利哥
We must take Jericho.
這是我們與應許之地間唯一的障礙了
It's all that stands between us and the promised land.
嘿   嘿
Hey. Hey!
白天才能取水
You can only collect water in daylight.
現在回家去  走  走
Go home now. Go. Go.
待在家裡
Stay indoors.
以色列人隨時可能進攻
The Israelites can attack at any time.
喇合  我的小妓女
Rahab, my little whore.
你在外頭做什麼   你知道這是不安全的
What are you doing out, hmm? You know it's not safe.
挺安全的
Safe enough.
沒有人是安全的
No one is safe.
我可以照顧自己
I can look after myself.
回去吧
Go home.
噓
Shh.
你們在這兒做什麼   以色列人
What are you doing here? Israelites!
出去  出去
Go. Go.
以色列人  救命
Israelites! Help!
以色列人
Israelites!
哥哥
Brother.
為了以色列
For Israel!
For Israel.
快
Quick.
這邊  再來點人
Over here! Get more men!
我們得躲進去  小心
We've got to get inside. Look out.
決不能讓他們跑了
They must not escape.
挨家挨戶搜
Go door to door.
進去
In here.
所有人  都回家去
Everyone, return to your homes.
人呢
Hello?
噓
Shh.
安靜  我保證不會傷害他
Keep quiet, and I promise I won't hurt him.
你發誓
Swear.
是的
Mmm.
-你們是以色列人  -你聽說過我們嗎
- You're Israelites.- You've heard about us?
你們有個能呼風喚雨  分開眾海的神
You have a god who commands the winds and parts the seas.
他讓我們擺脫奴役
He saved us from slavery.
我們是被他選中的子民
We are his chosen.
這座城裡的百姓忌憚你們
This whole city is terrified of you.
你們有如此神通廣大的神   我們怎麼可能打敗你們
How can we fight a people whose god can do that?
開門  開門
Open up! Open up!
-進去  -把門打開
Back inside. Open the door!
這條路能出去嗎
Can we get out that way?
幫幫我們  我們也會幫你的
Help us, and we will help you.
走吧
Go.
我會盡力拖延的
I'll stall them if I can.
打開門
Open the door!
跟我們一起走吧
Come with us.
不行  我還有家人
I can't. My family.
我們軍隊攻進來的時候   把這個掛你在門上
When our army comes, hang this on your door...
這樣他們就不會傷害你們
so they will know not to harm you.
你將免於這場災禍
You'll be passed over.
待在這兒
Stay here.
約書亞
Joshua!
告訴我  找到進城的方法了嗎   這突破口嗎
Tell me, did you find a way in? Is there a weakness?
城牆上沒有
Not in the walls...
但百姓心中有
but... in their hearts.
約書亞  我們遇到一個女人
Joshua, we met a woman.
她認為這座城已經被上帝拿下了
She thinks God has taken the city already.
他們知道上帝與我們同在   都陷入恐慌  不戰自潰
The people melt in fear because they know he is with us.
上帝確實與我們同在
God is with us.
但我們仍要想辦法進城
But we've still to find a way in.
摩西
Moses,
我的老朋友
my old friend,
你接下來會怎麼做
what would you do?
主啊  當我還是奴隸的時候
Lord, when I was a slave,
你向我展現了你的愛與能力
you showed me your love and your power.
你給了我新的生活
You have given me new life.
現在你想讓我們回頭嗎
Would you have us turn back?
你
Who...
你是誰
Who are you?
我祈禱你是幫助我們的
I pray you are with us...
不是幫助我們敵人的
and not with our enemies.
我是與神同在的
I am with God.
耶和華軍隊的元帥
Commander of the Lord's army.
我主有什麼話吩咐僕人
What does he ask of us?
主為摩西把紅海分開
The Lord parted the waters for Moses.
為你
For you...
主將塌陷城牆
He will split rock.
你必須這麼做
This is what you must do.
你們的一切兵丁要圍繞這城   一日圍繞一次
March around the city once a day with all the armed men.
六日都要這樣行
Do this for six days.
抬著約櫃
Carry the Ark with you.
裡面有神的戒律   這樣祂就與你同在
It contains God's commandments, and he is with you.
第七日
Then, on the seventh day,
你們要繞城七次
march around the city seven times.
祭司也要吹角
Then the priests should make a long blast' with a ram is horn.
你們一聽見角聲
As soon as you hear the sound of the trumpet...
眾百姓要大聲呼喊
All the people shall shout a great shout.
他們來了
It's happening!
榮耀將會降臨
Glory will come.
他的確是這世界的造物主
He truly is the shaper of the world.
我們要把這座城獻給主
We give this city to the Lord!
耶利哥是我們的
Jericho is ours!
只有妓女喇合與她家中所有的可以存活
Only Rahab the prostitute and her family may be spared,
這是上帝的旨意
for God said she must be spared...
因為她幫助了我們   因為她幫助了我們
- for the help she gave us. ...for the help she gave us.
上帝
God...
兌現了他的承諾
has kept his promise.
只要我們遵從主
If we obey the Lord,
萬事都可能
anything is possible!
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
Israel. Israel.
以色列  以色列
Israel! Israel!
約書亞死後一百年
A hundred years after Joshua,
以色列十二個部落遍布迦南
the 12 tribes of Israel have spread out across the promised land.
嘿
Hyah!
但他們四面楚歌
But hostile neighbours surround them.
嘿   嘿
Hyah! Hyah!
非利士人武器精良  訓練有素
Better armed and better trained,
是以色列人最致命的威脅
the Philistines are the deadliest threat.
由於缺少摩西和約書亞這樣傑出領袖的領導
Without great leaders like Moses or Joshua to unite them,
以色列人必須倚仗被稱為"士師"的本土英雄
the Israelites must rely on local heroes called judges...
參孫就是其中之一
people like Samson.
母親  來
Mother, come.
這種日子什麼時候才能到個頭啊
When will this all stop?
我也不知道
I don't know.
你必須反抗
You must fight them.
那是上帝想讓你做的  參孫
It's what God wants you to do, Samson.
那是上帝創造你的原因
It's why God created you.
記住他的信使跟我說的話
Remember what his messenger told me.
別害怕
Don't be afraid.
雖然你不能生育  但上帝會允你一個兒子
Though you are barren, God will give you a son.
感謝您
Thank you.
不過仔細聽好了
Listen carefully.
這是有條件的
There are conditions.
你當謹記  不可飲酒
See to it that you drink no alcohol...
不可吃不潔之物
and eat nothing unclean.
兒子出生後
And when your son is born,
他永遠不可剃頭
his hair must never be cut.
這是他作為拿細耳人的標記
This will be the sign that the boy is a Nazarite.
他自出生起  便歸上帝
He is given to God, from his birth to his death.
他會從非利士人手中拯救以色列
He will begin to deliver Israel from the Philistines.
你的力量源自上帝
Your strength comes from God.
你背負著趕走非利士人的使命
Your duty is to drive the Philistines away.
參孫沒有對抗非利士人
Instead of fighting the Philistines,
反而愛上了一個非利士女子  並娶她為妻
Samson falls in love... and marries one.
讓我和她談談  -當然
Let me talk to her. Of course.
嗯
Mmm.
母親
Mother,
難道愛不是源自上帝嗎
does love not come from God?
您想讓我怎麼辦
What would you have me do...
拋棄我愛的女人
reject the woman I fell in love with...
就因為她是非利士人嗎
just because she's a Philistine?
你的愛能保護我們不被他們傷害嗎
Will your love protect us from them?
參孫  參孫   參孫  參孫   參孫  參孫
Samson! Samson! Samson! Samson! Samson! Samson!
參孫  參孫  參孫
Samson! Samson! Samson!
我們得給以色列人點顏色瞧瞧
We need to send these Israelites a message,
讓他們明白我們的女人不是他們可以染指的
make it clear to them they cannot take our women.
我們兩族永遠不能通婚
Our people should never mix.
要怎麼抓住他
How are we going to get to him?
不用抓  他
We're not going to get... to him.
開門
Open up!
參孫在哪兒  -我不知道
Where is Samson? I-l don't know.
他在哪兒  -他不在這裡
Where is he? He's not here.
父親  父親  不要
Father! Father! No!
父親  不要
Father! No!
不要啊
No!
動手  -求你們了  不要這樣
- Do it. - Please, no.
你是我們民族的恥辱
You are a disgrace to our people.
求求你  -我求你  求你了
Oh, please. Please. Please, I beg you!
別碰她
Don't hurt her.
父親  不要
Father! No!
不  不要
No. No.
No. No!
求求你
Please.
求求你  求你們了  別這樣
Please, I'm begging you no.
求你們了  不要啊
Please, no.
不要
No!
不  不要
No! No!
不要
No!
為吾妻
For my wife.
非利士人
Philistines!
快來  -救救我們
Over here! Help us.
救命
Help us!
放了我們  放了我們
Free us. Free us!
抓住那個以色列人
Stop the Israelite!
只有一個人有這種能耐
One man did this.
他在哪兒  他的族人一定知道
Where is he? His people must know.
你
You!
你把參孫找來見我
You will bring Samson to me,
馬上把他找來
and you will do it quickly.
我一天不見到他   就殺一個以色列人
And for every day I do not see him, one of you will die...
即刻生效
starting now.
不  不  不要  求你了
No, no. No, no, please.
求你了  別
Please, no!
參孫
Samson!
Samson.
參孫
Samson?
Samson.
你在嗎
Are you there?
母親
Mother.
我沒想到您會來  請寬恕我
I wasn't expecting you. Forgive me.
我們是來勸你的  參孫   -勸？
- We have come to reason with you, Samson. - Reason?
你必須停止殺非利士人
You must stop the killing.
求你了
Please.
你殺了那麼多非利士人
For every Philistine you kill,
現在有兩個非利士人來找我們報仇了
two more appear, seeking revenge.
我只是以其人之道還治其人之身
As they did to me, so I have done to them.
如今非利士人是我們的統治者
The Philistines are our rulers now.
每個人都應該做他們認為對的事
Everyone must do what they think is right.
不  參孫
No, Samson.
你必須為你的人民  為上帝
You must do what is right for your people.
做正確的事
For God.
而不是為你自己
Not for yourself.
你必須犧牲自己  參孫
You must give yourself up, Samson.
母親  這是上帝的旨意嗎
Mother, is this what God wants?
我不確定
I'm not sure.
有時候   上帝在冥冥之中領導我們
Sometimes God leads us in ways we cannot see.
上帝會指引你的選擇
God will guide your choices.
來
Come.
讓開
Stand aside.
退後
Stand back.
Get back.
退開
Stay back.
你得到你的戰利品了
You have your prize.
我看到的是一個不過是個殺人犯
All I see is a common murderer.
你也好不到哪去
No worse than you.
為什麼要殺我的妻子
Why did you kill my wife?
為了給你
To teach you...
和你的族人一個教訓
and your people a lesson.
為拯救族人我願犧牲自己
I gave myself up to save my people.
現在你願意放了他們嗎
Will you leave them alone now?
如果我有更多的人手   我會把你們通通趕回
If I had more men, I'd drive you all...
屬於你們的荒蕪之地
back into the wilderness where you belong.
痛快地殺個片甲不留
I'd happily kill all of you.
殺了他
Kill him.
你背負著趕走非利士人的使命
Your duty is to drive the Philistines away.
上帝會引導你
God will guide your choices.
我的耶和華神  是你嗎
My Lord God of Israel, is that you?
主啊
Lord,
這是你希望我做的嗎
is this what you want from me?
請引領我
Guide me, please.
過來
Come.
Come!
謝謝你
Thank you.
你叫什麼名字
What is your name?
我叫大利拉
My name is Delilah.
大袞[非利士人的神]
Dagon,
上帝  造物者  我們的神
god and creator, lord of our land,
請將參孫  我們的敵人
deliver into our hands...
我們民族的破壞者
our enemy, Samson,
交予我們手中
destroyer of our nation.
我們有參孫的消息了
We have news of Samson.
他找了個新女人
He's got a new woman.
一名非利士女子
A Philistine woman.
又一個
Another one?
她叫什麼名字
What's her name?
大利拉
Delilah.
我認識她
I know her.
帶她來見我
Bring her to me.
大利拉
Delilah,
感謝你能前來
thank you for coming.
你還是如此誘人
As beguiling as ever.
你想怎麼樣
What do you want?
讓我們聊聊吧   你選擇了參孫
Well, let's just have a little talk- about Samson.
真是稀奇
An interesting choice.
一個外族男人   為什麼要和他一起
Not one of us, of course. Why are you with him?
為什麼你想要知道
Why do you want to know?
別告訴我你關心他
Don't tell me you care about him.
你們倆墜入愛河了嗎
Is he in love with you?
你自己去問他
Ask him yourself.
他屠殺了我們成百上千個的族人
He's butchered hundreds of our people.
他變了
He's changed.
自從遇到我後  他已改過自新
He's a different man since he's met me.
你真的相信嗎
You really believe that?
他會繼續殺戮   直到我們找到辦法除掉他
He will go on killing until we find a way to stop him for good.
他的力量從何而來
Where does he get his strength?
他的秘密是什麼
What's his secret?
我不知道   他不會告訴我的
I don't know. He won't tell me.
試著說服他
Try to convince him.
你難道沒見識過他的能耐
Have you seen what he's capable of?
或許這個會有所幫助
Maybe this will help.
這是你的危險額外津貼
Call it danger money.
全都是你的
It's all for you.
但不是現在
Uh-uh. Not now.
等到我們知道了他的秘密才是
Not until we know his secret.
你為何如此強壯
Why are you so strong?
上帝與我同在  大利拉
God is with me, Delilah.
他賜我神力
He makes me strong.
"上帝與你同在"是什麼意思
What do you mean.'God is with you'?
他如何賜你神力
How does he make you strong?
我母親無法生育
My mother was barren.
上帝給了她一個孩子   我
God brought her a child- me.
但有些事情是我不能做的
But there are things I must not do.
比如說
Such as?
我從不剪我的頭髮
I have never cut my hair.
這是被禁止的
I am forbidden.
這代表著我對神的忠誠委身
A sign of my devotion.
倘若我剪了頭髮  我
If I cut my hair, I...
怎麼樣  親愛的
What, my love?
倘若你剪了頭髮會怎麼樣
What if you cut your hair?
上帝會收回我的神力
My God will take away all my strength.
我會變得同凡人一樣羸弱
I will be as weak as everyone else.
你不相信我嗎
You don't believe me?
不  參孫
No, Samson,
我相信
I do.
參孫
Samson!
哇 啊
Wha- Huh?
抓住他
Take him.
怎麼...
What...
你做了什麼
Wha- What have you done?
別自責
Don't feel bad.
不過就是你被賣了
Everyone has their price.
大利拉
Delilah.
仔細看看
Take a good look...
要記住你跟大利拉相遇的那天
and remember the day you first met the lovely Delilah.
你再也見不到她了
You will never see her again.
把他帶走
Take him away.
走   走
Move. Move!
快點
Quickly.
帶他過去
Bring him through.
失明的以色列人
Blind Israelite!
我站不住了
I am weak.
讓我靠著什麼吧
Stand me against something.
主啊
Lord...
安靜
Quiet!
主啊
Lord,
如果我是你選召的人  別放棄我
if I am yours, remember me now.
讓能我再次擁有力量
Strengthen me once more.
你的上帝已經拋棄你了  參孫
Your god has abandoned you, Samson.
是你使我雙目失明的
You are the man who took away my eyes.
我很高興
I am glad of it,
因為幽暗幫助我思考
for the darkness helps me think.
你的上帝拋棄了你
Your god has deserted you...
收回了你的神力
and taken your strength with him.
不...
No.
我現在能更清楚地看到他
I can see him more clearly than ever.
他讓我徹底毀了你們
He wants me to destroy you all!
結束了  參孫
It's over, Samson.
阻止他
Stop him!
殺了他
Kill him!
快
- Now!
參孫的犧牲也同時終結了數千非利士人的性命
Samson's sacrifice kills thousands,
但他再也無法單槍匹馬地反抗非利士人了
but he could never defeat the Philistines on his own.
先知撒母耳動員以色列人以上帝之名團結一致
The prophet Samuel has urged the people to unite in Gods name.
上帝至高無上
There is no one like the Lord.
但經過了數十年的努力
But after decades of struggle,
他還是沒能阻止非利士人的入侵
he, too, has failed to halt the Philistines.
先知  我們在等你
Prophet, we await you.
人們的耐心日漸喪失
And the people's patience is wearing thin.
你們有什麼煩惱
So what is it that troubles you?
我們很感激您  先知
We are grateful, prophet.
您已領導我們多年
You have led us for many years.
是上帝領導我們
God has led us.
撒母耳
Samuel,
但您年齡漸長
you are not as young as you were.
我們很憂心
We are worried.
在您之後  誰來和上帝說話
Who will speak to the Lord after you?
誰會領導我們對抗非利士人
Who will lead us against the Philistines?
我的兒子們會繼承
My sons will inherit my place.
您的兒子們都腐敗無能
Your sons are corrupt.
我的兒子們從小就信仰上帝  謹遵教條
My sons have been brought up to trust in God and obey his laws.
我為你們做的每件事   都是因為我行上帝之道
Everything I have done for you I have done because I walk in God's ways.
我們知道他們收受賄賂
We know that they take bribes.
人盡皆知
Everyone knows it.
他們敗壞了您的名聲
They shame your good name.
所以
So,
當您不在
when you are gone...
非利士人卷土重來
and the Philistines return...
我們能指望您的兒子們  呼求上帝時
and we look to your sons to call on God,
上帝會回應嗎
will God answer?
不  不會
No. He will not.
那你們想怎麼樣
Then what do you want?
一位王
A king.
就像其他國家一樣
As other nations have.
但看看那些國家的王都幹了什麼
But look what other nations' kings do.
他們變成暴君  奴役自己的子民
They become tyrants. They make slaves of their people.
由上帝選中的王不會這樣
Not if they are chosen by God,
再由正直的先知為其膏立
anointed by his righteous prophet...
就是您
by You.
你是要違抗上帝嗎
You would reject our God?
上帝給予我們這片土地
God promised us this land.
這是上帝的國度
This is God's kingdom.
他是唯一的王
He is our only king.
您是上帝之耳  撒母耳
You have the ear of the Lord, Samuel.
您必須請求他為我們選一位王
You must ask him to choose a king for us.
你們都出去  所有人都出去
Leave me alone. All of you.
我曾奉獻所有
I have given everything.
現在他們不願聽從我的領導
Now they have rejected me...
上帝
and you, God.
如果您想讓我為他們找一位王
But if you say I should give them a king,
我當然會這樣做
then of course I will.
但誰能擔此重任呢
But who should it be?
我明白了
I see...
那不可能是我
that could never be me.
但我仍然是你的先知
But I will still be your prophet.
我可以指導你的王
I can guide your king.
掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
掃羅
Saul.
願你能依循上帝的律法
May you reign justly and wisely...
公正且有智慧治理這地
and according to God's law.
我膏你作以色列的第一位王
I anoint you the first king of Israel.
我想，作為神的先知
May I, as God's prophet,
我可以盡我所能幫助你
help you in any way I can.
在以色列歷史上開始了一個新時代
A new era in Israelite history is beginning...
掃羅  掃羅   先知和君王的時代
- Saul! Saul! - The period of prophets and kings.
他們必須共同努力，以確保應許之地
They must work together to secure the promised land.
掃羅  掃羅
Saul! Saul! Saul!
下集《聖經》預告
Next time on The Bible.
都準備好了
Are the men ready?
他們準備好了
They're ready.
我們必須在我們開戰前獻祭
We must make a sacrifice before we attack.
願上帝饒恕你
May God forgive you!
好好當你的王。 把獻祭的事交給我
Be a king. Leave the job of priest to me.
你雖是我們的先知  但我是你的王
You are our prophet, but I am your king!
上帝所給的，祂隨時可以收回
What the Lord gives, he can take away.
上帝與我同在
God is with me!
你和他在一起  我王  是嗎
Are you with him, Lord, really?
你悖逆了耶和華
You disobeyed the Lord.
他必將你的王國  給大衛
He has torn your kingdom from you and given it to David.
輪到你當王了   你難道不會剪除我的後裔？   不會讓我臭名？
When you have my crown, will you not kill my descendants, bury my name?
耶路撒冷  我們的新家園
Jerusalem, our new home.
王永遠不可能超越上帝
A king is never above his god.
你濫用你的權力
You abused your power.
你奪走了你最忠誠的僕人烏利亞的一切
You took everything from your most loyal servant.
你奪人妻子  然後又害死了他
You took his wife, then you took his life.
你以為上帝對此一無所知嗎
You think God doesn't see everything?
我是他所選召的
I am his chosen one.
大衛   由於你蔑視上帝
David, he will bring disaster on your house.
必有災禍臨到你家
We shall see.